[Music]
do
hello good evening good day everybody i
hope you're all doing well
and welcome to the latest the 84th
episode of ask abhijit
and as you know today is going to be a
video chat episode which means that i
need to share the video chat link
and hopefully i will get some new faces
today so
let me share the link uh here it is
uh one second let me share that
and let me pin
it on the chat now you guys will be able
to join
the video chat if you click on that link
all right so
let's wait for some people to join in
the meanwhile let me see who all is here
with us
good evening good day to all of you and
i can see some people have already
joined
i am going to
i would like to see some new people
new faces this time
hopefully
so okay so let's let's uh
let us begin
with i can already see lots of people
have joined
so whom should i bring in first let's
bring in mr shirinath
hello good evening sir
how are you doing sir
i'm fine sir
all right what's your question where are
you from first of all where are you from
i am originally from tamil nadu i live
in mumbai now
aye zayn how old are you
i am 12.
fantastic fantastic so what's your
question sir
sir my question is that should our
country first develop socially and
culturally or should our country
first develop technologically
right that is the age-old question
should we
i mean
the question that lots of people have is
that is is india right to invest money
in the space program and in defense and
various things or should we first
develop should we first eradicate
poverty and all that the answer is very
simple it has to go hand in hand you
cannot
ignore
any aspect of development it has to all
happen simultaneously and there are lots
of examples if you look at
the past 100 years of history you will
see that japan was destroyed after the
second world war they developed
everything at the same time the same
goes for south korea vietnam all the
other countries that have come out of
poverty come out of the
third world status and gone to the first
world cities they have done all the
development simultaneously the japanese
are obviously as you know one of the
mo
they are most likely the most
technologically advanced society in the
world today in 1947 45 japan was a
destroyed country it had been totally
annihilated in the second world war so
they became technologically advanced
along with whatever other development
they did socially and removing people
from poverty and all that so it has to
go in hand in hand if you ignore let's
say something like the space program and
say that let's first eradicate poverty
then you're gonna be several decades
behind the rest of the world by the time
you've caught up with other things so it
has to all go hand in hand right
so i hope that answers your question
thank you sir
nice to meet you thank you bye
all right let's bring in
um
let's bring in mr harsh takur
hello
okay so hello g set hello how are you
i'm fine what about you
i'm good where are you from
i'm from delhi
all right what's your question sir okay
okay so my question is about the art
invasion things so you know i was you
you brought professor niraj dry on your
live program last last time and i and i
searched uh searching about this you
know so he said in a podcast that of the
presence of
foreign india is around 18 000 years old
and i was and he also accepted that the
step immigrants uh came into india so if
if the step immigrants came into india
how can the
presence of our neighbor in india can be
18 000 years old so this is what i
wanted to ask
okay so do we know what kind of genetic
lineage is the step immigrants were
carrying do we know that
they must be carrying r1 or r1b the
ancestry or the
you know okay so
okay i get it all right so the question
is that you are saying that if some step
ancestor is there then how come r1a1a is
indian i don't see a logical connection
i don't see a logical connection between
these all right so let me explain what
it is right so the step ancestry
whatever is there in india is recent
recent like the past three thousand
years only that's if you if you listen
to the conversation i had with dr niraj
rai he explains very clearly that the
step ancestry is very minimal it's a
very small amount of ancestry that comes
from the step it has happened in the
past 3000 or so years and if you look at
this step ancestry itself it itself
seems to originate in it in india at a
much earlier date
okay so that's what you need to pay
attention when you listen and the second
thing is this if you look at the
approximate date at which r1 a1a
originated it's between 18 to 30 000
years before today yes and the most
likely place of origin is india and the
same applies for r1b2
even for r1b most likely as dr niraja
himself said most likely even r1b
originates in india now the yamnaya
lineages are almost exclusively r1b what
does that tell you it tells you that
even the yamnaya were originally indians
so i think that
that puts the entire matter to rest it's
only a question of time before the
papers are published and then even that
question uh that it's not been published
will go away so i think it's very clear
now from the data that we have from the
analysis that the doctor needed i
presented the other day
are you not convinced still i think
you're still not convinced
no it's just a little bit confusing that
whenever these people write the people
like david drake of the harvard medical
school whenever they write paper they
put things like
iranian so the question so the question
then arises is that whom do you want to
trust there are two experts one says a
one says be whom do you trust the
problem with indians i'm not saying you
specifically the problem with most
indians is we tend to trust the
foreigner more than the indian are they
foreign that has to be true so please
let's change our mindset all right we
have one of the best experts in the
world dr neeraj
who has already gone on record on this
channel and he has demonstrated what
things are like so
i think it is time for us to trust our
experts as well right
all right so thank you for the question
nice meeting you
thank you bye
okay who will come in next let me bring
in mr tejas
i am unable to see mr teve just for what
so let me try it again
looks like his uh devices are not
working let's bring in somebody else
whom shall we bring in
uh i will bring in people whose faces
are visible i will not bring in people
whose faces are not visible so please
understand that
uh
in the meanwhile let's bring in mr udit
hello
hello sir how are you sir
i'm very well where are you from sir
sir i am from delhi but um i live in
saudi arabia for now so i came last
section also i asked the russian
question like
in the last episode i was there okay so
today's
history sir
so when we talk about delhi sir what do
we
where do we where does delhi originate
from
and then how does it come here like till
i'm not asking to give you you should
that you should give a detailed
explanation like in short can you tell
like where it originated from like when
was delivered made
okay the history of delhi i think the
oldest see there is a there is a
see i haven't i am not personally very
much acquainted with delhi i've been
there only briefly a couple of times
very briefly but what i know is that
there is
a part of delhi in within the geography
of delhi which is called indar prasad
yes sir so that happens to be the
indraprasth of the mahabharat
it is the same location
and we don't quite know when the
mahabharata happened it happened minimum
i would say 5 000 or so years before
today yes i would say that that should
be the
i mean if archaeologists were to go to
the indira prasa indrapath place that
region and do some excavations do some
some research then they'll be able to
actually find some evidence some data
that will be
able to help us date
how old the earliest settlement in this
region is so i think that's where it
needs to start but we know that the
location of the historical indra prasad
of the mahabharata is there right there
in delhi yes i think it's
so the dating of the mahabharata and the
dating of delhi i think they are they go
hand in hand once we have a good idea a
good handle on how old indira prasad is
then we'll know that that should be the
origin of delhi so hastings it's all in
this region itself so yes that is that
that's where the clues lie yes right
thank you sir
thank you nice meeting you again bye
okay let's bring in
so my question is that
um uh if moon plays a major role in
um
woman
uh menstruation or uh
um pregnancy how come
human race will be on mars
that's an interesting question i've seen
the thing is that uh
like you said the menstrual cycle seemed
to coincide with the with the uh
phases of the moon 28 or so days i'm not
a great expert in this
uh so we have evolved on this planet and
the human species is about two million
or so years old and our ancestors before
the human species were all with various
kinds of apes so we have evolved in a
certain manner
so now if humans in the future were to
go to a different planet let's say
hypothetically mars then what will
happen
uh i don't think it should be quite a
very big problem
evolution happens over a time scale of
millions of years
so if humans will go to mars and and be
there for let's say a couple of million
years and we survive that long then
maybe we will see evolution happening in
a different direction in some manner
it's all speculative we don't even know
if humanity will last the next thousand
years the way it is going so i
so you know that's uh that's the way it
is but yeah it's a very interesting
question i think we should call some
evolutionary biologists something some
somebody like that and
ask this question to that person very
interesting question you asked
unfortunately i am not an evolutionary
biologist so i can give a broader
scientific perspective from the
perspective of the time scales of
evolution but very interesting question
i'm glad you people are asking such
intelligent questions so that's what i
can offer you thank you so much thank
you thank you so much nice meeting you
ma'am thank you bye-bye
meet you sir
all right who else shall we bring in let
us bring in my good friend soham
chaudhary
sir china is colonized by communist
ideology communism it is itself a
western ideology communism is created by
the german philosopher karl marx karl
marx was born in
uh
tired
so second that means that the
communism
is created by the
western philosopher named karl marx
the
china was was a democratic country from
1912 to 1949
but after the chinese award which has
happened from 1927 to 1949 communist
party of china over to the democratic
elected government and established the
people's republic of china
so my main question is that
sir my question is that why nobody is
talking about this topic that communism
is a western ideology
capitalist western ideology
has a thousand reasons capitalism like
western ireland but why nobody is
discussing the communism western
ideology
well let's talk about it
of course it is a western ideology
it it has its origins in
who was it uh karl marx himself was uh
he was influenced by an earlier german
uh scholar thinker i don't remember was
it hegel most likely hegel it was so
that's the lineage
of this communist ideology socialism
communism it's all different um names
for essentially the same
line of thinking so you are right this
uh this
communism itself originates you could
say the overall father of communism is
the uh is this guy called karl marx i
don't consider him to be a philosopher
by by any stretch of the imagination but
yes he is the guy who came up with the
marxist ideology which became communism
and all that eventually it's even been
called maoism with some
uh with a little bit of reinterpretation
so china today is no longer a communist
country we have to understand that too
china practices capitalism it's an out
and out capitalistic mercantilist
country
even even countries like china china
north korea vietnam and cuba who oppose
the western ideology still follows the
communism which is the western ideology
so they don't oppose western ideology
they have opposed western imperialism
understand that
they opposed western imperialism what is
imperialism it means that a foreign
power which is more powerful than you
comes and tells you how to do your
things how to live your life they they
try and interfere with the internal
affairs of your country that is
imperialism and so so that's what was
happening in the 20th century whether
you're talking about vietnam whether you
talk about korea why is korea divided
into two it's because of external
factors the korean people did not divide
the country into two pieces it is that
the influence of china and the ussr on
one hand and the u.s on another hand
which divided korea so this is foreign
interference the same thing was
happening in vietnam it was divided into
north and south and so on
so they don't oppose western ideology
western thought they oppose western
imperialism they hope they have been
opposing
attempts to for
from western powers to interfere in
their internal affairs so understand
that it is not an opposition of the
western uh culture or ideology if you
look at the vietnamese people lots of
them even speak french even today and
lots of them live western lifestyles and
eat pizzas and burgers and things like
that so it's not about about opposing
western culture or western uh ideology
it's about opposing imperialism right so
vietnam even today is a communist
country more or less they also practice
a form of capitalism actually right
yes exactly you're right and north korea
is not quite a communist country it's a
one-party authoritarian dictatorship
so you can call it communism but it's
actually that thing so the main domain
yeah
so what i'm saying is it's it's quite
complex it's not as simple and
monochromatic as it it seems to be
coffee complexities
so communism is of course of western
ideology and these guys don't oppose
western ideology they oppose imperialism
which they should
got it
capitalism
communism
you are right you're right so it's a
very interesting point that we have
brought out thank you nice to see you
again
yes sir
next sport comes
all right all right thank you thank you
bye
okay who else shall we bring in let us
bring in uh mr tarun kumar who is
raising his hand
hello how are you sir
hello sir can you see me am i visible
and audible
you are visible in audible sir where are
you from thank you i'm from telangana
i'm from hyderabad
so i have a
long question for you it's regarding
aryan vision theory
so i belong to a telangana ethnicity and
telangana speaking family
so it's different from what you see in
the commercial popular fiction space of
telugu cinema or telugu literature
so my question specifically is about
aryan invasion theory because as a child
growing up in a telugu family we have
lot of familiarities or telugu is almost
similar to sanskrit in many ways even
the vocabulary is as you know 70 or 65
percent related to sanskrit
so in intermediate when we had to choose
a secondary language i chose sanskrit
because many of my friends told me that
it happens to be very
similar sounding to telugu so i thought
it would be easier for me so i went
ahead and chose sanskrit as my second
language and i was so surprised to see
that though the script was in devanagari
the words the soundings everything the
etymology was uh
you know almost similar to telugu so
at that point i had no idea about what
aryan invasion theory is and who aryans
are
uh supposedly and that i
being a south indian i am a dravidian i
didn't knew that before until i started
uh diving a bit deeper into history and
uh started learning more about a culture
and stuff like that so now when i hear
people saying that south indians are
ethnically or culturally or whatever
genetically different from north indians
because
north indians are supposed to be the
so-called aryans who were
who invaded our country 1500 in 15 000
bc or 1500 bc sorry so i find it so
baffling because even the words that we
use are
very uh you know sanskrit related even
in hindi you use most of the words they
are from urdu right so i'll give you a
few examples sir i'm not uh very much
would you say i'm not a voracious reader
of telugu but i have
a good knowledge about the language and
the sounds and all of that so for
radhari we use
you know there are so many words which
are directly related to sanskrit and you
don't get to hear them often in any
other language of course you get to hear
a lot of sanskrit words words in kannada
as well but i think no one has ever
countered the aryan invasion theory with
uh with the point of linguistics so my
question to you in short is why wouldn't
we counter the uh so-called
uh elite historians with this argument
that when you study the linguistic
deeply enough uh the south indian
languages are more aryan to speak of
so has there been
in this direction
certainly certainly linguistics is one
of the major battlegrounds when it comes
to the iron invasion theory there is
this entire
theory that has been constructed from
the linguistic perspective of the
indo-european language family so they
say that german is closer to sanskrit
than telugu is that's the because telugu
is supposedly part of the dravidian
language family so there is this
battleground in linguistics as well
they have created a language family
called the indo-european language family
and dravidian languages are not part of
the
language family
and yet if you if you do a comparative
analysis of sanskrit and german and
sanskrit then telugu for instance you
will find that telugu and sanskrit have
so much more in common than sanskrit
than german or sanskrit in french or
sanskrit in latin for instance or
sanskrit and greek so it is
abundantly clear that any indian
language from the south southern regions
of india whether it is telugu whether it
is kannada whether it is tamil whether
it is tulu whether it is malayalam or
anything else they are way closer to
sanskrit than are any of the european
languages so actually shouldn't all of
these indian languages be part of the
same language family instead of trying
to categorize sanskrit in a language
family that that also has european
languages it is it makes no sense so
what needs to happen
is we need to
re-analyze the languages linguistically
a priori starting from scratch from a
proper scientific paninion perspective
that's what needs to happen right now
linguistics is not a science they call
it a science but it's all based on
consensus building and all that
consensus building is not science it's
politics
you see that's what's happening and it's
a bunch of western linguists who have
taken over and they decide what is right
what is wrong so linguistics currently
is is completely pseudo scientific it's
totally incorrect
and uh so so what you have pointed out
is absolutely valid telugu and all the
other uh southern indian languages are
much much closer to sanskrit than any
uh extra indian language
so so it is certainly one of the things
that that we can use to prove that these
people are incorrect in the
categorization or classification of
indian people into two ethnicities or
two races and that's also been debunked
by the science of genetics i mean you
and me if we compare the genetics we
will have almost everything in common
just
the skin color or whatever else you have
it's all superficial it all depends on
climatic factors or on where your
ancestors have been for the past
thousand or so years so that that also
affects your skin color your eye color
hair color everything else
so these are superficial factors
actually beneath the skin we are very
much alike whether whether it's somebody
in north india west india is somebody in
kerala for instance or somebody in
bengal we are all the same genetically
and linguistically we have so much in
common much more than
what we have in common with other
countries so your point is valid and
that's why i have been saying that we
need to re-examine the linguistics of
india a priori from scratch in a
scientific manner so that is still
something that's not happened yet we
still don't even have any instead of
linguistics in the country
yes sir i'm really sorry to interrupt
you here but i just have a small humble
request for mine because uh you are a
very influential person uh in this uh
you know right set of arguments and uh
you have access to many uh you know
brilliant thinkers of our country yes so
that uh could you please make a podcast
with uh uh people like neeraj
or sanjay dikshit or any other people
from these uh
you know
the indic thinkers who have a good bit
of knowledge about the linguistics or
some you can call on some linguist
experts especially telugu linguistic
expert and then you can compare sanskrit
and telugu and maybe try to bring in
some argument
because i think this argument this uh
you know uh this factual argument will
really help uh this destroying this and
debunking the yeah so i already have a
podcast with dr neeraj and i will
certainly take up your suggestion thank
you all right i'm going to end it here
because there are people waiting but
thank you very much very good points
nice to meet you sir nice to meet you
thank you
all right
let's bring in mr tejaswa what's again
hello
can you see me can you hear me
could you speak yes yes please
foreign
if you look at the equations of special
but from an external observer's
perspective clock speed
so an external observer will age
faster than you so the higher your
velocity is the slower you will age
that's the thing you get in special
relativity
what is the behavior
at relativistic speeds of
of clocks of of length contraction time
dilation
and so on and so forth
i cannot give you an intuitive
understanding or intuitive heinie
equations can tell you
all right sir
nice to meet you thank you thank you for
the question
bye
all right who else
shall shall we bring in let us bring in
lots of people are
let's bring in mr sahas
well hello
hello sir hello am i ordered hello i can
hear you
yes sir where are you
i'm from up sir
all right
so that's a question so my
question is that we hear these western
countries talking about human rights and
um war crimes sir my question is why
aren't the americans demonized for
nuking an entire country
and more than my follow-up question is
what led to these bombings and uh wasn't
there any other way than uh totally
dismantling a
country through nuclear arms
right so the reason they are not
demonized or they're not called out for
doing this is because they control the
narrative they control the entertainment
industry hollywood which portrays
americans as the superheroes as the
people who are morally righteous all the
time they never do a wrong thing and
secondly they control the entire media
the entire media that we consume the
english-speaking media because indians
only consume english english media more
or less internationally so we only see
their perspective the narratives they
build the british broadcasting
corporation is is essentially a
propaganda arm of the british and all
the american outlets media outlets are
propaganda arms of the u.s establishment
that's why you don't see this happening
that's why you don't see any other
perspective if you were to able to read
russian or chinese you would see
different perspectives but that's what
we cannot do and that's why we only see
a one-dimensional perspective now why
why did why did the bombings happen
because they wanted to test
the bombs on on civilians i suppose you
know because these are not white people
these are some brown people or asian
people let a few of them die
right
so human rights don't apply to non-white
and non-western people it's it's as
simple as that so they and and the uh
justification they would like to give
you is that by doing the bombings they
actually saved lives because otherwise
the war would have gone on for another
six months or one year and more people
would have died so we actually did a
good thing we killed fewer people
so that's the kind of moral
justification they use which is all
nonsense
right
that's so ironical sir
yes thank you sir
and what you're doing is would be
remembered for years to come sir thank
you so much thank you so much thank you
thank you nice meeting you bye
all right let's bring in
whom shall i bring in i shall bring in
mr
kushagrabhalla
hello
hello how are you doing from
i can hear you yes
uh i think i can't hear you
well i can hear myself i think everybody
else can hear me
yes
okay i think that's a
yeah i i'll bring you back later i'll
bring you back later because you are not
able to hear you i mean you're not able
to hear me uh let's bring in somebody
else
and
let's bring in mr manmath tiwari
well hello sir how are you doing
i am from now on
i am in class 12th currently so my
question is that there were
in the pre-christian era there were many
religions throughout the world like
throughout the global landscape they
were through many religions but
none of them conducted convergence so
badly and so brutally that they would
torture people to such bad extents that
they would end up dying and convert out
of fear but
in the case of christianity and islam
both being an abrahamic religion
converted each and like they took over
countries like within a night
they took down our islamists and
christianized countries over like two to
three years and like using brutal means
to convert everyone
even
the abrahamic religion but they didn't
convert like that brutally so
does does not that make us think that
christianity and islam were not
religious basically they were a
political move to maintain global
hegemony like we can also take the fact
into considering that both of these
religions almost appeared from the same
region of the world
yes
yes i get a question the abrahamic
religions their origin is with the
prophet abraham
who was a judah jewish prophet and these
three religions are called the religions
of the book they are essentially the
same um
essentially a very similar worldview
ideology mindset and these are
religions that emerged out of the desert
in the desert what happens is that you
need
the desert climate is brutal it's very
harsh you need extreme discipline and
military structure in in your society in
order to survive so that's the kind of
religion that emerged from there and
it's it's been able to take over the
world because
because it is an organized these are
organized religions
and because they are organized along
military lines
and like you say there is this
propensity to convert which no other
polytheistic religion has so it's just
the inherent property that all the
abrahamic religions have however when
you talk about judaism they are
organized differently they are not
organized in a top down military manner
the the organization from in from the
perspective of judaism is more organic
and it is more decentralized so the
other two religions abroad religions are
centralized in a military fashion so
that's why judaism behaves differently
they don't have this focus on conversion
if somebody wants to convert there is a
long process i believe and so on
so that's just how it is the it's it's
well known what what the history is so
it is an inherent characteristic of the
abrahamic
yes it is it is certainly a political
military all of it combined
right okay so thank big fans of what's
up what small request that please just
bring out your podcast on that does
wasn't what i'm very eagerly waiting for
i didn't get it sorry
so i was saying that please can you
bring out a podcast on that
i'm eagerly waiting for it all right all
right sure thanks for the suggestion i
will certainly look into that
thank you
thank you so much thank you so much nice
meeting you bye
okay who else do we bring in let's bring
in
mr chinmoy mr chinmoy bora
hello hello sir hello sir how are you
i'm very well
where i from
sir i'm from assam
all right nice to meet you sir what's
your question
sir my question is why is china so
interested in claiming arunachal pradesh
means the locals there claimed that
many times the chinese army tried to
enter ownership
why is it so sir
the chinese have this propensity to try
and keep all of their neighbors under
constant pressure
okay they are an expansionist power and
they are a hegemonic power now the only
major threat to china or challenge to
china in the entirety of asia is just
one country which is india
and they want to keep india constantly
on the back foot so that is the reason
why they are always doing this this the
this strategy of pinpricks constant
pinpricks create an incursion there and
including the here including in ladakh
in question in arunachal pradesh or
somewhere else use pakistan to
destabilize india on the western border
and so on and so forth it's been a
constant strategy for the past 50 plus
years ever since they
conquered and a next tibet illegally so
that's been a constant chinese strategy
and
they actually they are worried that if
india rises economically and militarily
then their plans will be thrown into
you know into this array
so that's why they have this right now
the in the past they also had these uh
these geographical boundary disputes
with the russians in the 1960s they
almost went to war with russia they had
this significant and very serious border
clashes with russia so it's a constant
ever present feature of the chinese
communist party's foreign policy to to
have border disputes and all these
problems with all their neighbors they
have territorial claims with every
single neighbor they have
so it's not only about india but the
focus is more on india because india is
the only major power that can challenge
the chinese so that's why they are
claiming arunachal pradesh
see before the 2000s they were not
claiming pradesh
because at that time india had not
recognized tibet as a part of china
so it is in the 2000s i believe early
2000 that the indian prime minister
officially recognized tibet as part of
china
and once that happened they immediately
made a claim
so this indian policy has been really
silly and really counterproductive so
that's the reason why all of this is
happening but i hope i explained over
from a larger perspective why the
chinese have this attitude of constantly
doing this right sir thank you very much
for breaking the question i hope
thank you sir
most welcome nice meeting you take care
bye-bye
all right who else
shall we bring in let's bring in mr uh
jitin nair
hello
can't hear you sir
you're not audible unmute yourself
ah yes i can hear you now yes sir where
are you from
sir your thoughts on tipu sultan i am
from maharashtra mumbai
uh my thoughts on devastating i can give
you one word monster and his
hello
yes i think tipu sultan was a was a very
brutal evil
king and
so yeah in in one word a brutal
monstrous barbarian and somebody who
should not be glorified all right sir
uh sir one more uh sir one question
one question per person sorry the rule
is one question suggestion
sir can you make videos in
hindi no sir not at this point
in the future maybe i'll do it i have
another channel which in which i have
made one livestream in hindi so it's
certainly something i will
keep uh oh no you know i may do it in
the future at this immediate time it is
not possible because i'm focusing on
certain things but certainly in the
future i may do it certainly so in the
long run yes
all right yeah thank you nice meeting
you sir
okay um
let's bring in mr will smith no no no no
no no will smith uh let's bring in mr
sandeep chaudhary
hello sir
hi sir
big fans how are you doing where are you
from
uh good i'm from uh delhi
all right what's your question
so my question is uh what what's your
take uh on russia and ukraine crisis are
they gonna attack uh they're going to be
a war or it's just a threat
all right good question so what what we
are witnessing right now is that we are
witnessing a certain kind of uh
cooperation between the chinese and the
russians because their national
interests to some extent they converge
right now so what we are witnessing is
that russian the russians are exerting
geopolitical pressure in eastern europe
in ukraine right now that's the pressure
point and the chinese at the same time
are exerting geopolitical pressure
in the south china sea
in
uh with respect to taiwan
so what we are seeing is an attempt to
uh keep the united states off balance
with two pressure points in two
different regions of the world right so
i think that uh i am not expecting the
russians to invade ukraine they will
keep threatening it that the russian
threat to eastern europe is permanent
it's never going away the russians can
threaten to destabilize eastern europe
any time they wish to right
so it is simply in my opinion and in the
opinion of other experts too
i'm not quite an expert but in the
opinion of geopolitical analysis and
strategists it seems to be uh
something that is happening in
coordination with the chinese right now
we have the uh winter olympic games that
are happening as we speak right now in
china so the chinese want this to go off
smoothly there's been a diplomatic
boycott of these games from the west
from india as well so they are worried
that they will lose face if there is a
if there is all of this happening in the
game so that they want the games to go
off smoothly so maybe they are
coordinating with the russians to exert
a kind of certain kind of pressure in
ukraine to divert the united states
attention away from china at this point
in time
so uh
will the russians invade i don't think
they will invade right now but in the
future they may possibly invade if the
time is right they feel and if they
stand to gain something more than they
stand to lose in that case they may
invade so it's a complex situation i
don't think an invasion is actually
imminent immediately
right sir okay thank you sir good night
thank you good night nice meeting you
okay um
who shall i bring in
let's bring in mr abhishek chaudhary
hello
hello is a huge fan and thank you asked
questions so many times and
unfortunately it was never picked and
i'm speaking face-to-face to you very
happy
right so i
i'm from new delhi
new delhi all right what's your question
yeah
yes so i just want to ask like according
to you who is bigger threat to india is
it the communist
or is it extreme islamist and second
part is the government taking
a sufficient step to protect us from
them and if not what you and i as a
common citizen can do to protect
ourselves
see you and as common citizens can't do
much the government has to take care of
the national interest now in my opinion
the real threat to india internally
comes from outside forces
you have all these ngos and all these
various bodies in india that act as
conduits for foreign money and influence
into india
and these ngos and various other
organizations they then go on and fund
the various forces internal forces that
they just mentioned
so all of this will immediately stop if
the influx of foreign money stops
now the question is why is the influx of
foreign money not stopping it's because
there are certain powers that are way
way more powerful than india
who are pressurizing india to keep
allowing certain things to happen so it
is actually all happening because of
foreign influence there are see
in the world there are certain forces
there are there are certain powers that
transcend national boundaries
and there are
and they they essentially influence and
interfere with the internal affairs of
countries all across the world
so that's what's happening in india
right now so what needs to happen is
india needs to rise economically and at
the same time militarily once india's
economy crosses let's say 10 trillion
dollars of gdp
then india will be a different kind of
beast
then we will be able to push back
against this sort of foreign
interference in india and once that
happens all the internal
threats that we are facing will
automatically evaporate so that is
what's happening it's actually what we
are witnessing are symptoms of foreign
interference in india that's what's
really the big threat
thank you thank you sir and one request
uh you and i really love like the
podcast that you are doing right now
like bringing different guests um so i
just request that if you can also bring
in major gaurav arya uh you two are my
like biggest hero so i would love to see
both of you together on one screen thank
you for the suggestion thank you i'll
certainly keep that in mind thank you
thank you thank you bye bye
all right
who else do we bring in let us bring in
mr man of shah
i can't see you sir
you're not visible
your
camera doesn't seem to be working
okay let's bring him in
at another time let's bring in somebody
else um
ah somebody's dancing well hello
hi hi sir
hello shires right where are you from
my question for you is that
when are we going to
take back pakistan occupied kashmir and
i have some explanation as well
uh the balochistan the people from
balochistan are attacking pakistani army
right now right because and china
pakistan economic corridor passes from
pakistan occupied kashmir
right
so if we try to take back pakistani
occupied kashmir then china we have to
reap the chinese
so when are we doing that if suppose
from
10 years from now if we become
a 10 trillion dollar economy or a 12
trillion dollar economy
so is is that the right time date
backbox covers and how will we do it
right so when are we taking back pok
well if i were to disclose that to you
then all of our enemies will know so i
will not do that
see it's like this
let me explain see you can do things at
any given point in time but there is
always a price that you must pay when
you indulge in a military action
you're going to take certain steps and
your adversaries will retaliate in
certain ways
so there is always a balance of power
and you have to pick the best moment
when you know that you will have to pay
the least possible price when the time
is right that's when you strike now when
is the time right you never announce
when the time is right
right exactly see
so the
the enemy has certain vulnerabilities
like you saying there are certain things
happening in balochistan
and the enemy is essentially in pakistan
they have taken over some parts of our
territory but right now they are being
aided and abetted by a much larger power
china
right correct right now china is quite
stable they don't have any problems so
like i said we have to pick the right
time right now china is strong they are
able to support pakistan but there may
be a time in the future that we may
actually see coming if we have the right
way of looking at things
when
there may be certain problems so the
average age in china right now is 38 or
39 years the average age of hours is
around 26 27 years so if the average age
of china increases right when the
people who work at factories the
manufacturing plants of that
people
as they grow older maybe they will not
work that way and when
i think we have a good chance right now
because the average age is very less
comparatively to china so if
we might achieve our peak in the next 10
years or 15 years
what do you mean so when i'm talking
about the right time i'm not talking
about looking at the average age it's
nothing to do with the average age of a
country
you're looking at other geopolitical
factors you're looking at the internal
stability of the country you're looking
at leadership struggles you're looking
at other factors you're not looking at
the average age even if the average age
is 18 you will still still have
sufficient soldiers who are 20 year old
or 25 years old
so that is not the issue the issue is
the overall internal stability and the
ability to project power
that's what you're looking at so in from
that perspective when the time is right
we should act the time is not right
right now
okay sir thank you thank you very much
thank you good question nice meeting you
okay who do we bring in
let us bring in mr mega lok giri
hello
can't hear you sir i can't hear you
yeah so my question to you is what was
the relationship between odisha and
southeast
asia
excellent question excellent question
that's a that is a relationship that
almost nobody in india knows i think
very few udiya people also know about
this yes
nomenclature of the region so the
relationship between kalinga and eastern
asia goes back at least three thousand
years
so the uh people of orissa where see the
entirety of india was a maritime nation
east west not so i mean
the two coastal regions of india the
western coast the eastern coast so orisa
as we know is in the eastern coast so
the orisa the people of kalinga were
seafarers they were maritime traders and
they had this ancient trade relationship
with uh southeast asia essentially the
cambodia region cambodia etc with in the
vietnam region laos region
with which they have they have been
trading at least three thousand years
before today and they used to go in
these ships called boita and even today
they there is this tradition of boita
banana
exactly that's a very very old tradition
it goes back around 3000 years
and we know that there is significant
cultural influence of kalinga
in southeast asia even today i think
they still call indians is calling you
know that even today yeah in indonesia
sir i have also like read in wikipedia
about like the bay of bengal was in some
time was actually known as kalinga sagar
it is the british it is the british who
named all of these regions they first
colonized bengal so they called called
this this part of the indian ocean the
bay of bengal it is incorrect to call it
it is a colonial name given to it even
the south china sea should be the champa
the champa kingdom was another kingdom
in southeast asia that was deeply
influenced by kalinga
if you look at vietnam the about 2000
years ago we had the kingdom of funan
which was founded by a trader a merchant
from kalinga who married a local
princess so there is there is a
considerable influence of kalinga of
orissa in southeast asia it's visible
even today even if you look at the
various uh dances the classical dances
of bali of cambodia etc you will see
elements of odc dance in that yeah i
think yes sir so all of this is there
and unfortunately we in india are not
taught about the incredible incredible
ancient history of kalinga and how
long before the cholas it is kalinga who
who indianized southeast asia
conquered this region about a thousand
years before today but two thousand
years before the cholas
the people of kalinga were already doing
uh the acculturation of southeast asia
from from the indian perspective so very
interesting history i wish it would be
taught better yes
obviously so thank you so much sir for
bringing with me
my my pleasure nice meeting you sir nice
meeting you thank you bye
okay
let's bring in mr arvind dubai
hello hello hello good evening
good evening good evening from
[Music]
six months and uh
i tried to join him but i am unable to
uh
he said that
before 23rd of january
that
government is not taking
most appropriate step current government
is not taking most appropriate steps to
bring nathazie back where he was
i feel i just want your comment on that
i feel uh
bjp is a party
who wants to win the election
they say they want to
rule out the congress completely or
they want them to venice but of in the
all india perspective congress is the
main opposition
not the local parties
and somewhere more than 150 seats they
used to fight directly with the congress
where they've been
but on the contrary when they go to
fight with the local parties
they
there are chances that they lose
so it's their
government
particularly wants that congress to be
hanged on the loggerhead
so that
they have a kind of
winning probability remaining always
do so what's your question
do you think it's
right or not
okay okay so yeah right i get you i get
the point you're making
anything else
it's a politically uh political thing
rather than the uh nationally
nationalist thing
because
yeah i get it i get it so the
perspective we have to see the bigger
picture if the bjp doesn't win elections
they cannot take the country in the
right direction
in electoral politics the most important
thing is winning elections winning
elections
you have to win the election that is the
most important thing and then you can
make whatever changes you want to make
slowly gradually but if you lose an
election everything is wasted all the
effort you put in over the past seven
ten years will be totally wasted because
whoever comes to power next will undo
everything
therefore i would say we have to look at
it from that perspective also that if
the government does not concentrate on
elections then all the work they are
doing will be undone so i do not see it
as something that is that is incorrect
they have to do it they have no option
no no no no i
um
[Music]
when is the next
session
[Music]
nice meeting you thank you bye
okay let us bring in
mr arun
hello
hi hi abhijit uh pleasure meeting you
and it is great
i'm basically uh right now in hong kong
but i am from india like i mean
obviously i stay in uh you know my
hometown is hyderabad so that's where
i'm from
yeah right so so yeah so i basically had
a question right like uh i have been to
different countries like you know
indonesia like i've you know gone across
the different cultures of bali and also
in cambodia and there's a huge you know
heavy presence of hindu culture you can
see that in the architecture you can see
that in the day-to-day life and i see
also that they are enriching their
culture on day-to-day basis which i feel
in india is like kind of degrading over
the time but i do see the kind of
renaissance you know stage that's
happening right now so and i also see
that they have a dance that they do
which is the dance which is pretty much
uh the depiction of ramayana
and it's beautiful right so i want to
understand like you know what is it that
we can do as indians to try and you know
uh not only like glorify our history but
also how we can try and spread more of
the you know innate capabilities of our
uh you know ancestors that they had in
terms of
knowledge right so what needs to happen
in india is some form of cultural
renaissance it's not enough to become
prosperous financially it's all at all
it's a try it's happening slowly but
yeah indian culture when we talk about
it there needs to be some sort of a
cultural renaissance which means that
the common man woman child the citizens
of india need to patronize indian
culture right now what's happening is
all the money is being spent on
bollywood or whatever other cheap form
of entertainment we have but that is not
indian culture they are not promoting
indian culture bollywood does not even
represent indian culture
so we have our own ancient heritage so
many different forms of classical dance
classical music architecture painting so
many things so we need to find ways of
trying to revive that we have such
beautiful forms of dance like odyssey
dance we have the
yaksha ghana which is a more of a folk
dance kind of thing and so many other
things we also have so many different
kinds of architecture all of that right
yeah so we need to find ways
as citizens to to patronize and to
promote our own indigenous forms of art
and culture the government will have
some things like the sangeet academy or
whatever but it doesn't may have much of
an effect if you look at what's popular
on youtube you will see only bollywood
you will not see any indian classical
dance or music or anything so uh
so we need to try and find ways of
popularizing all this because like you
just stated all of the dances in south
east asia whether it is the upcera dance
or the dance in cambodia all of these
dances they are all influenced by indian
classical dancers especially odc dance
and like you said there are the various
beautiful depictions of the ramayana
whether it is in thailand whether it's
in burma whether it's in cambodia laos
etc even bali so indian culture is
valued more in southeast asia than in
india itself that is the terrible thing
that we are witnessing so we need to
find ways of of
promoting our culture again and that
will only happen if there is more
awareness of our own culture within the
within the citizenry right so
that that's what needs to happen i don't
have answer specific answers as to how
we can make it happen but we need to try
and explore our own culture more than
bollywood or something like that you
know
right that's what i would say sir yeah
so i have a small request and i really
loved your uh you know talk on the
ancestry and the migration from the
so-called africa and how it uh you know
kind of evolved from there uh so i'm
also a geneticist so i really like you
know uh yeah i love this whole topic and
i work actually on the whole migration
patterns and all that but mostly
yeah it's mostly on the overall european
ancestry and other stuff and uh of
course i'm very curious about the indian
uh you know ancestry part and that's why
i would love to know more about the
south south uh indian ancestry and i
think there are a lot of papers which
you know do talk about it and you spoke
about the tribal part of the andaman
nicobar and all of that uh and yeah i
wanted to know if you can ever touch
base on you know krishna devaraya
kingdom because that's something which
is fascinates a lot probably if you can
do a one episode on that or something
that'll be amazing and i do follow every
episode of here so yeah
thank you so much
it's a very interesting uh part of our
history and certainly we have not i have
not touched upon in great detail so i'll
certainly do that in the future thank
you thank you very much
thank you nice meeting you thank you bye
bye
okay um
who else comes in let's bring in mr
rishi raj
hello
hello sir uh i am rishi rajiv but i'm in
class 10 sir
listen sir what should be an ideal job
for an indian sir i'm in class 10th but
my teachers and
her parents are forcing me to take
engineering those are what should be an
ideal job so that india can become a
global superpower
engineering
[Laughter]
see if you want to make india
a developed country
then you need to build a lot of
infrastructure lots of roads railways
highways airports other kinds of
infrastructure we need equipment
machinery we need to industrialize all
of that is engineering so if you want to
contribute in that manner of course
engineering will help but again when you
talk about the ideal job
it depends on person to person everybody
has a different kind of aptitude what
they are good at some people will be
good in engineering some people will be
good in sports some people will be good
in cultural arts
you have to find what you're best at and
in case you are good at engineering and
science and all that then you should
certainly go for that and of course
there is a good future in engineering
you will get a good job you will have a
good
stable career and maybe you you can do
lots of good things for the country so
you have to first understand yourself
what are your aptitudes what are your
strengths
and on the basis of that you can make
decisions but engineering is certainly
good if you want to think of the
long-term future of the country it's
certainly good
okay thank you
thank you nice meeting you
let's bring in miss avika
hello
hi can you hear me hello hello hi
up yes ma'am what's your question
why didn't
god say kill gandhi
why did mr nathal go gandhi well i have
not studied mr nathoram gotz's career in
detail but i think he wrote i mean there
is a book available uh online and other
places
why i killed mr gandhi or something like
that i think he gave an entire
explanation of his actions when he was
under trial i haven't read it personally
so i cannot go into why he did that but
all that information is certainly
available his entire testimony his
entire explanation of why he took this
step of assassinating mr gandhi is is
available so i would i would recommend
to you that please look it up please
acquire the text and study it and then
you will have the answer i am not an
expert in in this specific matter i have
not studied it in great detail
so i cannot give you a concrete answer
but i can give you the direction so
check it out
thank you bye thank you nice meeting you
bye
okay uh
um let's bring in uh whom shall i bring
in let's bring in mr mr domnick
well hello
hello sir
how are you doing where are you from
namaste i'm from maharashtra
all right sir what's your question
so my question is uh
uh how how can we have
like a bring the uh develop the
strongman characteristics
like uh
uh
like
we see today uh
all around that uh our focus is not what
we want to do
a lot of distractions are there so
how can we develop that strongman
characteristics and uh
do what we want to do and take this
country forward
right right good question so right now
there is so much noise there is so there
are so many distractions in the world
social media and all kinds of other
things so we are always distracted
there's always something to see
something to watch some video to watch
some tick tock or whatever it is these
days
uh and so on and so forth there are so
many distractions so you saw you
essentially are
constantly consuming something
and you just can't think that's what's
happening so what needs to what what
people need to do is they need to
stay away from social media i mean don't
don't be completely immersed in social
media 24x7 and uh
try to spend time with yourself first of
all learn meditation that's how you
learn to focus
how do you if you want to focus your
mind on things you need to learn how to
meditate even if you started 10 minutes
a day so there is one thing that can
help you and if you want to develop the
strong man attitude like you say then
you need to be physically and mentally
strong
mental strength is augmented by physical
strength if you are physically strong if
you are like a strong person physically
that adds to the mental strength and the
confidence that you have so you have to
develop yourself
thoroughly from a 360 360 degree
perspective
you have to find ways to grow mentally
intellectually maybe spiritually learn
new things and you need to take care of
your body you need to
develop your body to its full potential
so that is something that is neglected
greatly among indian kids teenagers etc
you only are focusing on studying
another thing and you don't have the
time to develop your body physically
either work out or play sports or
something like that so all these things
need to happen and you need to try and
understand who you really are which you
can only do if you spend time alone if
you spend time with yourself
and you need to understand who you are
and go in the direction that is best for
you based on your strengths your
personal strengths
so that is what i can give you that's
what i can offer you in brief that's how
you can
go ahead and develop
yourself to the fullest extent into your
fullest potential
yes i had one suggestion uh so yes uh
can you bring someone a legal expert to
explain like the constitution and all
those things the legal things
good suggestion i will certainly keep
that in mind
all right thank you thank you so you
have been an inspiration for me thank
you
thank you so much thank you so much nice
meeting you bye
all right let's bring in somebody else
who has been waiting for some time
uh let's bring in mr sharang
hello
hi i can't hear you can't hear you
can you hear me now
can you bring the mic closer to your
mouth
yeah no is it better
it's audible somewhat go ahead please
what's your question where
all right what's your question sir
um my question is regarding the
similarities we have between
darwin's evolution theory and our
dashout
so
there is a quite similarity in between
them so does it mean that we already had
a knowledge of it uh
and if yes i mean why it is not
scientifically written
as a form or journal or something
right see what happened 1000 years
before today is that all of our
universities see india was a country of
very high standards of education we had
universities all across the country
north south east west uh we had
universities like taksha sheila nalanda
tilhara vikram sheila sharda pete and so
on and so forth all across the country
one thousand years ago the turks invaded
india occupied india and they destroyed
every single university every university
had a huge library we know that the
university of nalanda when the library
was burned it burned for several months
so all of this textual information
all the academic information that was
part of the university libraries was all
burned to ashes and therefore whatever
knowledge we had has was destroyed so in
case we had texts on evolution from an
indian perspective those are gone and
that's why we don't have the knowledge
today it doesn't mean it did not exist
if a library burns for months imagine
how much knowledge was there how much
text was there scientific text text
would have been there literally
literature
astronomy physics chemistry mathematics
biology pharmacology toxicology history
all of that would be there
it was all destroyed and that's why
today we don't have the answers but it
doesn't mean it was not there at the
time now when you talk about the
dash of taras there is clearly uh it
clearly resembles evolution it starts
with
the fish then the tortoise then the
dwarf then the larger humans and so on
so it clearly represents some form of
evolution but why is it not in the
journal form because all the journals
were burned so that's what i can say sir
that's why we lost all of our knowledge
so it means we had we had knowledge of
that so it's quite it's quite likely we
had all that knowledge it's quite likely
okay thank you sir
thank you nice meeting you
okay let's bring in the next person
let's bring in somebody who's been
waiting mr nitin
hello
can't hear you so i can't hear you
hello sir how are you
i'm very well how are you sir where are
you from i'm good i'm good thank you i'm
from pune uh okay basically i had like
uh two questions you may choose which
one to answer
uh one is uh
i have heard about the hundred plants uh
hundred year plan of
habitating uh on mars
like uh
there are there have been a few theories
by uh mr elon musk to uh
make it habitable uh mass habitable and
uh there are a few scientists who are
suggesting a 100 year plan for
for that month to be a habit a habitable
planet so uh there is a reason why water
is not there on the planet and it was
there earlier uh it does not have the
magnetic field that earth has and also
earth has this 23.5 degree uh tilt
because of the moon that we have so uh
even if we succeed to make it habitable
it but it won't be sustainable
so how scientists are claiming that uh
they'll be able to make a mass habitable
that is first question the second
question is uh why do we have this uh
uh the bhagavad
rather than there are so many gitas that
we have in our culture why are the
specific
is
so famous
so you may choose which one to answer uh
okay so let's let's go with the first
one the one about mars because there is
more of my strength science more than
the other thing
so uh
so what you're saying is that even if we
are able to terraform mass let's say
and uh
have water on the planet again and so on
you're saying that because of the
absence of a magnetic field again that
will not be
sustainable and again it will only
evaporate right that's what you're
saying
so the thing is this the absence of the
magnetic field is indeed a fact
and in the past we the the planet mars
had water lots of water flowing water
and it's all gone today what happened is
that the magnetic field disappeared
there must have been a magnetic field a
weaker one in the past
but for whatever reason maybe the core
solidified and the magnetic field went
away and because of that because of the
bombardment from solar wind cosmic rays
etc slowly all the
water
dissociated away into hydrogen and
oxygen and it disappeared but today even
today
there is water which is in the form of
ice on the poles of the of the planet
and also most likely under the surface
under the soil of the planet and we see
we can see evidence of that
so if we were to liquefy the water again
and create
a different kind of atmosphere then for
this process of the water disappearing
again to happen it would take millions
of years it would take millions of years
now we don't think as a species in terms
of millions of years our species is
about 2 million years old and homo
sapiens is at most a quarter of a
million years old so when you're talking
about a time scale of millions of years
over which water disappears it's not
important for us if water is there for
the next thousand years it's enough for
us right
so that's why it is a plan that makes
sense but it is just a dream right now
it is just a dream terra forming a
planet is not is not joke it will take
at least uh a few centuries for the
entire process to be completed at least
a few centuries maybe a thousand years
so it's it's a it's something that's
still in the realm of science fiction
it's not something that can be done
right now we don't have the resources
and the capabilities of actually doing
it unless we start using nukes all over
the place which obviously is not
advisable
so right now the first thing is let's
get to mars and get back once and then
we'll take it from there
getting back once would be uh really a
challenge for human beings
indeed indeed yes exactly so right
thank you sir it was really nice talking
to you i'm a great nice talking to you
nice meeting you
thank you so much thank you so much
bye bye
all right
um
who else do we bring in
let's bring in mr siddharth
winter olympics which is happening in
beijing and the second is
can it be a possibility that india has
played double
could they stabilize pakistan at some
point
it is certainly possible that india may
have played certain cards may be playing
certain cards maybe the effects will be
visible later maybe they are being maybe
they are visible right now so right now
if you look at what's happening in
balochistan there is this
i think just yesterday or day before
yesterday there was this attack by
balochistan freedom fighters on and on
the pakistani army outpost they were
able to capture the outpost and they
were able to get inside and defend it
for quite some time lots of pakistani
soldiers apparently have have been
neutralized in this action
so this sort of action it's it's not
easy for somebody to do it without
proper support you need proper training
you need really good training to do this
you need the right equipment also the
right supplies because if you're gonna
fire for like 20 30 hours you need
ammunition for that you need rifles and
weapons that will jam and that will not
stop that will not fail
so clearly
this is a well-planned operation if it
if it is the way we are hearing it to be
so so obviously it's possible that
obviously what i would say is that it's
it's not possible for the freedom
fighters to do all this without proper
external support now the only question
is where did they get the support from
so if you look at the weaponry which
they had it was actually american
weaponry m16 rifles night vision scopes
and various other things so that clearly
indicates it came from the north from
afghanistan where the americans left so
much
equipment
so it seems to indicate some kind of
linkage between the balochistan freedom
fighters and the taliban
right now taliban is supposedly
pakistanis the pakistani puppet but not
quite pakis the taliban are actually
pashtun nationalists and they have a big
border issue with pakistan they want to
reclaim territory from pakistan so it's
a complex situation and it's quite
possible that there may be in
involvement of a larger power as well
like you said like mr duval has been
state has stated in the past it is quite
possible but i don't have actual
evidence but one can certainly speculate
thank you so much
thank you nice meeting you
thank you bye
let's bring in mr rishikesh who has been
waiting for some time hello sir
hi sir um hi how are you where are you
from thank you hi i'm doing good i'm
from visagapatnam or i'm audi actually
but i've been here for some time
all right so
so my question is uh it's it's not
necessarily i'll actually explain it
so sir in india we follow a democratic
system which is based on the ideas that
were been imposed from like you know
from our colonizers and because of that
while we are a civilization which has
existed for like thousands of years
recordedly which is confirmed
we still today struggle to implement
five-year plans
while we should be a nation which which
should have concrete century plans at
the minimum
and because of this a lot of you know
youth suffer because of this so while we
have the
youngest youth population in the world
which is like 26 years
a lot of them are under distress because
they don't get to choose what they want
to do and at the end of the day those
who are capable of doing something
generally move out and we like you
mentioned in your older videos you have
become an exporter for digital cooleys
and the country greatly suffers because
of it
but now we are seeing that you know like
the countries which based their growth
on the basis of you know
looting goods and like you know assets
from other countries they have adopted
democratic systems and now they have
started observing an uprise in their own
countries like
yes there is
some resistance that's being observed
so like amidst all of these things
follows a democratic system and that's
exactly why people's ideology is like
you know dictate which direction the
government has to go and that's exactly
why the current government is actually
worried for what it's going to do in
five years
so do we see some good future for the
country in like the next 100 years
because it will be tragic if this
continues in the long run
and it would in my opinion
yeah
right so the points that you have
specified are 100 valid what we see in
india today is that
the young people the youth
don't have
sufficient options
there may be one or two options that
they can take otherwise go out of the
country and explore options elsewhere
that's the situation that we are in and
essentially the what's happened is that
for 50 60 years
india did not change at all it was run
as if it is still under foreign
occupation under foreign colonization
it's only in the last decade or so that
we are seeing some movement in the right
direction now you can see pro progress
you can see growth you can see the
massive build up of infrastructure which
which needs uh engineering jobs and
things like that but we are still a long
way to go from today and the reason why
progress is so slow is that we have this
federal system in which the central
government will have a certain plan but
the local governments federal
governments they will have other ideas
and they will oppose whatever the center
is trying to do and that's what the
nation is always constantly fighting
itself from within and that's where all
the energy goes in all the money and all
the effort all the energy is wasted only
in all of this internal friction
and
very little progress happens because of
that so clearly the indian system needs
to change now it's not going to change
today
but hopefully in the next 10 20 years
there will be somebody
with the with the
force of will
to
to make the country change what we need
is a new constitution a new way of
governance a new form of governance the
current form of governance is just
adopted wholesale from the small island
of england it is not
it is not something that is suitable for
a subcontinent-sized nation and that's
why we need a different form of
governance a more centralized form of
governance with with uh
with more democracy at the local lower
levels but overall the country should be
unified in going in the right direction
so that is a process that needs to
happen i am still quite positive that in
the next 20 30 next 10 20 years we'll
see significant changes because there is
something called momentum right now the
momentum is slowly building up but if it
is a if if we are able to sustain it for
the next 10 or 20 years we're gonna see
massive changes happening so it's all
about continuing the momentum that's
what i would say so like uh regarding
that only because of the external
influence we see that it's very easy for
a idea which is like you know counter to
the nation's growth is very easily
supported by external influence like we
see movies which
which promote an entirely contra like
you know contrasting idea which should
support the nation's growth so like is
it possible that you know like if
someone in the countries starts funding
uh like you know ideas like from
promoting ideas through movies or
anything that actually support the
growth of the nation is that a
possibility
it is certainly certainly a very good
idea we can certainly change the mindset
the cultural orientation of the country
with the using the entertainment
industry with the media and all that so
if somebody with this sufficient amount
of resources funding would start let's
say a new ott otp platform whatever they
call it and promote indian culture it
would certainly have a very big impact
the audio visual medium is very
influential in the 21st century and
social media too and the entertainment
industry too so it's certainly a low
hanging fruit which if somebody with
with the right amount of resources and
funding would want to do it it's
certainly very much possible so it this
is an avenue that we can certainly
explore but we will need funding for
that but funding is available in the
country we are actually a very rich
country money is there it's all about
how we use it
exactly right
yeah thank you thank you very much thank
you very good questions nice meeting you
sir
thanks
very much thank you very much thanks bye
okay let's bring in who has been waiting
for some time let's bring in mr abbay
hello
hello sir can you hear me sir
i can hear you yes sir
i'm from hyderabad
and
my question is actually about the first
cold war
so
in the first quality as we know that
the soviet union decided to create it so
you said that just because of mikhail
gorbachev's
policies of
more democracy last north and
perestroika and slowly they started to
lose control over the
eastern states of
the eastern europe europe and so do you
think
[Music]
there is any
involvement of the united states in all
this process of disintegration because i
have watched this
video of yuri besmanov and he said that
americans have been demoralized
during the cold war era and america was
very in
danger from the leftists in america but
finally as we see the result was just
the soviet union's integrated
so do you really think there's an
environment of united states
in the disintegration of the soviet
union
all right so like you said yuri benjamin
was a soviet defector to the west he
defected via india actually and in the
usa disclosed that there is this uh
soviet campaign to destabilize the u.s
to influence the u.s ideologically etc
and the majority of the effort was going
into that not into spying so that's what
he disclosed now we find that the cold
war actually was won by the americans
and it's the soviet union that
disintegrated so clearly there must have
been american efforts also
at influencing
events within the ussr and that has not
been disclosed right because they have
been able to keep it secret that's what
it means
uh the country did not disagree
disintegrate by itself
obviously there are external factors
involved and the only external factor we
can think of of that magnitude is the us
because there were two poles at the time
it was a bipolar world the ussr and the
us were the two poles the two
superpowers so the us was able to
prevail
so that's what happened clearly i mean
it's it's well known that the americans
in spite had had spies in the ussr many
of them were able to escape some of them
were caught and whatever consequences
they had to face they faced
so it was something that was happening
from both sides the ussr was trying to
influence the us ideologically subvert
the u.s population ideologically and the
u.s was doing various things on ussr
soil as well now today you will find
that all the marxist socialism ideas
that the soviets were pursuing and
promoting they have taken root in the
united states today
the u.s is the if you look at the
population the orientation is more
socialistic than capitalistic today
they are demonizing capitalism they are
talking about socialism marxism left and
the whole country is turning left so
actually that would indicate that the
seeds that were planted at that time
they have kind of they're kind of
bearing fruit today it's an interesting
process right
right sir good question thank you sir
thank you nice meetings
yeah bye
okay
mr aryan has been waiting for a while
hello
uh thank you very much sir uh can you
hear me
i can hear yourself where are you from
uh sir i'm from delhi uh sir my question
is i have been reading about this albert
einstein and all carl young like
psychologist and i have been found very
interesting thing that
a certain period of time in europe there
was a monoglot society in science
monoglot system
i've been reading this in an article
also so in which there was only one
common language used as a scientific
use in science that is latin after
sometimes it became a polyglot system
like french
spanish and german mainly
again it became a monoglot
through the rise of germany
and i assume that even if a strong
superpower rise like at the time in
1900s it was germany so many scientists
learned gentlemen even einstein and many
scientists knows german because german
was prominent language at that time in
science society
now it has also become a monoclonal
society and now the language has changed
to english so my first question is is it
possible as the china is
now we all know that it is aspire to
rise as a
superpower and if it
hypothetically at least we think if he
if it defeats the usa
will it change the
it possible to change english
is it possible to change english as a
common language in science because i
don't think that it is possible and
it is easy
because many okay
so look see you were saying that so so
what you are uh
asserting is that it's impossible to
displace english and replace it with
chinese as of today right so it all
depends on the time scale that you're
looking at if you're looking at the next
five years it's not going to happen if
you're looking at the next 10 years it's
not going to happen but if you're
looking at the next 50 or 100 years it
may happen
right
these changes they happen on large time
scales it won't happen in a week or a
month or a year it may happen over two
three decades if the chinese are able to
displace the us as the superpower now
like you said in the past there have
been other languages that have been the
essentially the the hegemonic language
for instance isaac newton wrote all of
his uh
all of his the the the the
the works that he wrote the principia
and the principle etc they were written
in latin even though he was an english
man right so there was a time when latin
was the
predominant predominating language
then if you look at the early 20th
century late 19th century the entire
development of quantum mechanics was
done with
via papers written mostly in german and
some in french
now the americans because of their
victory in the second world war
they again
were able to impose english as the
global language and yet
the ussr scientists soviet scientists
would write all their papers all of the
research in russian only and therefore
it was important for physicists at the
time the 1670s to actually know russian
how to read russian now today we have
english in the future there could be a
different language so these changes that
happen over long periods of time it
won't happen in five years ten years
maybe 50 years or 100 years period you
will have a new language emerging maybe
100 years from today so it's certainly
something that can happen
that's how the world keeps evolving and
is this changing english as a language
in science is actually good for india
no it is not good for india it is
terrible for india sanskrit is the most
superior language in the world it is a
much more scientific language it has so
much
much broader and richer vocabulary
it has much more nuance than english
english is an inferior language but
unfortunately because of the hegemony of
the anglo-spheric world today we are all
using english most of us are maybe
better in english than ever in our own
native language so this is a consequence
of mental colonization which we all have
including me
but english is terrible for india i want
the future generations to be speaking a
native language their native language
and sanskrit is a civilizational
language that's what needs to happen
thank you very much
thank you nice meeting you so good
question thank you bye
okay let us take one more question for
today
let's bring in mr kabir who has been
waiting for some time hello sir
hello sir
hello how are you
from
so i'm from merit
merit taker said what's your question
so my question is sir
like in the congo
the duke of congo killed hundreds and
thousands of people
and
the culture of the congo was changed
drastically
and today we see that almost all the
population is converted into
christianity so even after the
independence the why don't they revert
back to their root or
indigenous culture
very good question see what's happened
is that they have destroyed the local
culture and religion whatever it was
so thoroughly and they have brainwashed
the people so thoroughly that they now
regard their ancestral culture as
inferior
that's what's happened that's the kind
of mindset they put into people and what
they have done is that they have reduced
africa to complete destitution and they
have made africa completely dependent on
aid from western countries which makes
the local people feel that the west is
superior to us and therefore we should
try to emulate their culture their
language their religion and all that see
what they have done is this is called
neo-imperial imperialism you first do
colonialism you you conquer a country
you take out all the resources destroy
the economy impoverish the country and
then what you do is you reconfigure the
country you draw boundaries artificial
boundaries in the country and each of
the small
independent states that you create
should be such that they are unable to
sustain themselves on their own and they
are completely dependent on you even
after their so-called independence for
decades and decades and decades that is
called neocolonism and that's what's
still happening in africa and that's why
the people of africa because of this
situation the condition they are in they
feel the west is superior and therefore
we should try and either immigrate to
the west or try to be more western
without with our language our religion
our culture so that's what's happening
and that's why it is like that okay sir
sir why did you remove sir
short clip sir on your channel
because it is time for the channel to go
in a different direction now it is long
videos long conversations i am trying to
give you a different kind of value i
mean until now i have been speaking for
hundreds of hours so now i want to bring
in some really well qualified people
experts with different kinds of
knowledge and they will also give you
some really good information i want to
give as much knowledge as much value in
as many different perspectives
as possible so that's what i'm trying to
do right now so the channel has to keep
evolving and changing if you stay the
same you don't progress no sir i think
it is very good sir
okay i'm glad you think that way thank
you sir
thank you nice meeting you sir take care
bye
shall i take one more question let's
take one more question um
whom shall i bring let's bring in mr
rakshit
hello
hi sir okay so i have two questions you
can choose either of the one or one
why why europe was the most dominant
country in the world during the 18th and
19th century even though we had america
russia japan they were powerful and some
of them were barbaric as well
my second question was
india was less than 300 billion economy
in 1990s and
during the before 2014 we were 1.92
trillion dollar and today we are 3.25
trillion dollar so we had a growth which
can be considered reasonably well so
what we can do to reach that 10 trillion
dollar mark which you mentioned all the
time so these are the two questions you
can pick anyone
okay let's take the second question so
our economy was very small until the
1990s there was almost no growth at all
for many decades it is called the
neheruvian rate of growth one percent or
two percent per year essentially what
the policies that mr narrow implemented
they stifled our growth and that's why
we did not grow at all for so many
decades even though we were so badly
impoverished now after the economic
liberalization of the early 90s our
growth started to accelerate and that's
why we are now approximately 3 000
trillion dollars uh
in gdp per annual gdp so what needs to
happen if we want to quickly reach 10
trillion
of economy of gdp what needs to happen
is we need to have a sustained period of
growth
of at least 10 percent every year at
least 10 percent so if you look at the
history of the chinese economy from the
for for a very long time for like more
than one or two decades they were
growing at more than 10 per year
sometimes 12 sometimes 13 sometimes even
15 percent and that's how they have been
able to change transform their economy
and become almost a media middle income
nation today and that's why they're the
second largest economy in the world
today so if india has to become a large
economy again and reclaim its historical
place
at the top of the food chain from the
economic perspective we need sustained
growth
large growth 10 plus every year for at
least the next 10 years minimum ideally
for the next two decades so the
government needs to find ways of
accelerating the growth and creating
sustained growth which you can do by by
investing in infrastructure by
industrializing the country and in
various other ways so that's what the
government needs to do and that's what
that's the direction in which india
needs to go
right and they're doing that so i have a
request uh could you please call some
expert on gupta dynasty and lata di
mukhta peda cause they are very
fascinating and they're very you know
intimidating if you want to call them
certainly very good suggestion i will
certainly look into this particular
thing thank you thank you have a great
thank you so much nice meeting you
thanks
okay but let's bring in one last person
let's bring in vaishnavi hello
hi sir i'm a very big fan of yours and i
really watch your all your videos my
heart is beating very fast right now
relax relax
i'm from new delhi and uh i'm very lucky
because you spoke to my husband a few
moments ago
i did
yes yes so
uh so my question is sir that i'm really
intrigued by area 51 in the america and
there are various theories surrounding
this uh topic also and also one of the
theories surrounding is that russia is
also hiding some information regarding
aliens so if it's true then why these
both countries are hiding this
information from the general public
okay good question so area 51 is a place
where there are so many claims that
there is there is some alien technology
alien artifacts all that we don't know
if it's true but let's let's
hypothetically consider the possibility
that they are actually hiding something
they are they're concealing some alien
technology there
and then the question which you uh raise
is why are they hiding it why are they
not revealing it the answer is very
simple if you have something that gives
you an advantage over your opponents
why would you reveal it to them
don't reveal it
if you have some secret weapon that
others which
that will help you win over the others
never reveal that secret always keep it
hidden your enemy should never know what
your strengths are it's as simple as
that therefore in case this is actually
true that they have some alien
technology etc they will never ever
revelate because it will give away the
advantage right
that's the answer
so do you think that america is
definitely experimenting on aliens and
this information uh is being shared by
the president of america also united
states of nation
i don't know i have no information
because i am not privy to such secret
classified information i think it's
unlikely that aliens have visited the
planet but in case it is true they will
not reveal it so
so i don't have any specific information
okay thank you sir thank you so much
good night
most welcome nice meeting you man bye
bye bye
let's let's do one more person
and the person is not visible
in
of what we refer as bharat mata does it
have a consciousness means does it
uh
align itself in such a manner that it
produces great leaders according to the
need of the time
okay that's an interesting question does
the land have consciousness well we
don't know if if land has consciousness
if consciousness is something that's
present in non-living materials and all
that i don't know about that that's
that's uh
that is a topic of debate in various
fields in spirituality in philosophy et
cetera so i don't know if if the land or
the geography is a consciousness and if
you're talking about great leaders in
the past 1000 years which greatly
leaders have produced
after raja raj and rajendra
then so
does it have an impact on the mind of a
person like if he believes that there is
a bigger entity than him
like if you believe that there is
something larger than you and something
that is giving you power and protection
it certainly helps you psychologically
it gives you more confidence so yes it
is always a good thing that's why people
who believe in god etc they they have
this advantage that they feel that they
have some extra force some extra power
that is supporting them so it does uh
help you psychologically in terms of
confidence and so on so forth it does
thank you speaker
thank you so much nice meeting you take
care bye
all right my dear friends i think that
brings us to the end of today's session
i can see more people waiting i
apologize to all of you i apologize
but we are done for today
so we will continue this it's it's great
fun taking your questions and talking to
all of you face to face and let's keep
doing this
so
thank you all again and until the next
time i wish you a good night a good day
wherever you are and i'll see you in the
next episode take care bye